<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<website name="Pebbles&apos; Program Page" home="index.html">
  <!-- Site Sections -->
  <section name="Home" file="index.html" nedstat="ADNQcQc5tT8Op5L39Ogb1cjZggeQ">
    <para>Welcome to Pebbles&apos; Program Page.</para>
    <para>
      Here you can find several tools written by Pebbles of Pandemonium; they will either be related to
      <acronym title="Final Fantasy XI">FFXI</acronym> Online, or to <acronym title="PlayOnline">POL</acronym> in general.
    </para>
    <news-headlines/>
    <para><span class="link-description">Pebbles can be contacted via email (pebbles DOT pandemonium AT telenet DOT be).</span></para>
  </section>
  <section name="News" file="news.html">
    <news/>
  </section>
  <section name="FAQ" file="faq.html">
    <para>
      <h3>1. What is POLUtils anyway?</h3>
      <p>
        POLUtils is a collection of utilities related to PlayOnline, Square/Enix' online gaming framework.<br/>
        It currently contains:<br/>
        <ul>
	  <li>an audio manager (with POL, TetraMaster and FFXI support - would add FMO support if I could get
	      someone to give me the info)</li>
	  <li>data browsers for Tetra Master and FFXI</li>
	  <li>an offline macro editor for FFXI</li>
	  <li>a configuration editor for FFXI</li>
	</ul>
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>2. What are the system requirements?</h3>
      <p>
        Well, POLUtils requires the .NET Framework 1.1 to be installed, and the Audio Manager has an additional
        dependency on Managed DirectX (part of DirectX 9 or higher) if you want audio playback (and that's a
        rather essential element of that particular tool).  Unfortunately, Managed DirectX is not automatically
        installed along with DirectX - you can find a suitable installer for it on the downloads page.<br/>
        As for Windows version, any version of windows that can install those two dependencies should do (which
        basically means Windows 98 or later).  Future versions of POLUtils may use the 2.0 framework, which will
        probably require Win2K or later.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>3. I get an exception saying Invalid Codepage - why is that?</h3>
      <p>
        FFXI uses a text encoding based on shift-jis, and it seems the .NET framework relies on a Windows code
        page to process shift-jis.  However, the shift-jis codepage isn't installed by default.  You can easily
        install it in one of two ways: either you enable support for East-Asian languages (Control Panel\Regional
        and Language Options\Languages), but that requires 230MB of disk space, or you can just make sure
        codepages 1250, 1251 and 932 are checked on the Advanced tab of the same control panel applet.<br/>
        As of version 0.5.0, POLUtils uses a handwritten encoding handler for FFXI, so no additional codepages
        should be needed.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>4. Why isn't POLUtils available in <em>&lt;insert language here&gt;</em>?</h3>
      <p>
	Easy - noone has volunteered to help with the translation yet.  If you want to provide the translation,
	let me know; all help is appreciated.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>5. Is POLUtils going to steal my passwords or destroy my PC?</h3>
      <p>
	I sure hope not ^^.  POLUtils currently never ever connects to the internet, so your passwords
	are safe.  As for destroying your PC, that's unlikely as well (of course, the .Net framework is
	Microsoft technology, so you never know).
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>6. Will you make a WinAmp plugin for .bgw/.spw files?</h3>
      <p>
	No.  I considered doing so, but decided against it since a) there already is such a plugin, and b) the
	WinAmp SDK is, well, crap (I never realized how great the foobar APIs were until I saw the WinAmp SDK).
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>7. The menus in the Macro Editor only show little squares instead of symbols, but I do have East-Asian supprt installed. Help!</h3>
      <p>
	This probably means you're using an older (pre-XP) version of Windows.  POLUtils has no control over the
	font of its menus; that's handled by the system.  Try setting the menu font (via the Appearance tab of
	the Display properties in the Control Panel) to Tahoma, that should work.
      </p>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section name="Download Area" file="downloads.html" nedstat="ADNQdQo0vLkP4XweMb5W1npl0G7w">
    <para>Here you can download Pebbles&apos; programs.</para>
    <downloads/>
  </section>
  <section name="Links" file="links.html">
    <para>This page contains various links you may (or may not) find useful.</para>
    <links/>
  </section>
  <!-- News Items -->
  <news file="news.html">
    <news-item title="foo_pol 1.2 Released" author="Pebbles" date="July 22nd, 2005">
      <p>As of the July patch, S/E has been using ATRAC-3 for music and sound effects in FFXI.
         I updated foo_pol to recognize those files, but it's unable to play them (ATRAC-3 is a
         proprietary codec by Sony; why they use it is beyond me as it's worse than MP3 quality-wise - they
         should have gone for Ogg Vorbis instead).  Unless some major bug is found, this will probably
         be the last foo_pol release until foobar2000 0.9 comes out.</p>
      <p>I also plan to move up the POLUtils 0.6.0.0 release - it won't have all the features I would
         like, but should be nice nonetheless.  It will also include EngrishOnry, a small utility
         to translate portions of a JP FFXI installation.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="Still not dead" author="Pebbles" date="July 6th, 2005">
      <p>POLUtils still isn't dead, I've just been doing other stuff; there's not much to report
         at the moment.  0.6.0.0 will be done when it's done.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.5.1 Release" author="Pebbles" date="May 6th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.5.1, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Fixed broken loading of Managed DirectSound.</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.5.0 Release" author="Pebbles" date="May 1st, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.5.0, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>If you have remarks/comments/gripes/corrections/suggestions/whatever, please, please let me know
         (email is on main page).</p>
      <p>I'm also interested in DAT file mappings - if you know what a particular DAT file contains, and it's
         not yet linked to from the data browser menu, let me know.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Improved installer; added warning message to make sure people only use installers they
	  dowload from the official page.
	</li><li>
	  Fully implemented character set conversion using internal translation tables - this means POLUtils
	  no longer depends on any Windows codepages; it should be fully Unicode.  There will probably still
	  be gaps in the extended mappings added by SE; if you see any &lt;BAD CHAR: xxxx&gt; markers, please
	  report them (and if possible, let me know what character shouldve been shown instead).
	</li><li>
	  Lots of improvement to the data browser.  The item viewer was completely overhauled, and a
	  "find item" dialog was added, with moderately poweful query capability.  Exporting item data
	  to XML or CSV is also fully supported (no progress window for it yet though).  Several more
	  string table formats are supported (titles, abilities, area dialog tables).
	</li><li>
	  The data browser has 2 settings of its own (not currently preserved between runs) - you can
	  opt to see a more detailed progress report (e.g. "loaded 5/200 items" instead of "loading items..."),
	  and you can choose to make the file scan abortable.  Either option slows down the file scans though,
	  so they're disabled by default.
	</li><li>
	  Added FFXI Config Editor.  Currently allows changing only resolution and sound effect count
	  (free editing, not limited options).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>New Bugs:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Lots. Probably.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Too many to mention.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Plans For Next Release</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Overhaul the macro editor.  If you have any layout/design suggestions, please let me know.
	</li><li>
	  Rework the menu system for the data browser, perhaps basing the menus completely on an XML file
	  that describes known DAT files.
	</li><li>
	  Rework the audio manager so that it doesn't do a full scan, but instead only scans parts of the
	  directory tree on an as-needed basis.  While not much an issue for the music files, scanning the
	  SFX files takes waaaay too long.
	</li><li>
	  (Maybe) Add a recipe database.
	</li><li>
	  Add a tool to compare exported item lists (mainly for my own use, so that i can report item data
	  changes after each patch).
	</li><li>
	  (Maybe) Extend the config editor to allow full configuration (would help people that use JP POL +
	  NA POL + 1 FFXI install, as that means no JP FFXIConfig).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="I ATEN'T DEAD" author="Pebbles" date="March 6th, 2005">
      <p>No, the POLUtils project isn't dead.  I am rewriting a lot of stuff (data browser, macro editor)
         and am writing a text decoder from scratch (good: no more codepage dependencies, bad: lots of
         boring mapping table data entry).  On top of all that, I plan to add an FFXI config editor
         (resolution / sample count already in; also looking into other stuff) and an item search (i.e.
         look for all items containing "Aketon" in their name or "Ranged Accuracy" in their description).</p>
      <p>This is all going to take some time, and I'm not going to release 0.5.0 until that's finished;
         so bear with me ^^.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="foo_pol 1.1 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 20th, 2005">
      <p>I'm release an update to foo_pol today. Nothing spectacular, but rather useful.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  There is a new "Fade Out (10 seconds)" loop option.  For looped files, this will cause
	  it to loop for a maximum of 10 seconds, with a slow fade.  This makes listening to looped
	  tracks more pleasant.  This feature was suggested by Feenicks on the FFXIOnline forums.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.4.0 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 16th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.4.0, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  POLUtils is deployed via an installer now - this also checks for the presence of the .NET
	  framework 1.1, to avoid unexpected and/or cryptic Windows errors.
	</li><li>
	  The language choice on the main dialog will now only list available options (and in its
	  native form).  Additionally, the selection will be preserved across runs.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  There was a logic error in the data browser - if a second item data file was opened, the
	  item icons of the first one were reused.  This is now fixed.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.3.5 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 15th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.3.5, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.<br/>
         This is really an intermediate release, there weren't enough major changes to
         warrant a 0.4 version.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  The data browser has a menu now, that allows you to easily find several kinds of "interesting" files
	  (maps, item data, etc.).
	</li><li>
	  The data browser now has support for item data - not quite all available info has been figured out
	  at the moment (e.g. Rare/Ex/NoAuction flags).
	</li><li>
	  The data browser will now scan files for any images they may contain (instead of just checking the
	  start of the file and displaying the first one it found).  Unfortunately, this can take some time,
	  and you cannot abort the scan at the moment.  I will look into making that more convenient (improving
	  the speed probably won't be possible, but I'll try the too) - however, threading doesn't play very
	  nice when Windows Forms controls are involved, so it's a bit tricky.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Some of the picture loading code was broken and/or missing - the current data browser should
	  support most formats (DXT1-DXT5 and the various bitmaps) properly.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.3 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 4th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.3, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  You can select the interface language - only small portions have been localized at the moment,
	  and only for Dutch and Japanese.  Volunteers will be needed to assist further.
	</li><li>
	  FFXI Data Browser - allows browsing the contents of the .DAT files of FFXI.<br/>
	  Currently, only string tables (e.g. ROM\97\17-57.DAT) and maps (e.g. ROM3\4\0-20.DAT) will be shown
	  (although some non-map images will also be shown (e.g. ROM\0\1.DAT, which contains the game's font,
	  and ROM\97\10.DAT, which has the treasure chest texture).<br/>
	  I'll probably add menus in the next version to help locate "interesting" files.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  POLUtils will refuse to start if no POL clients are installed (instead of crashing).
	</li><li>
	  The AudioManager now dynamically loads Managed DirectSound - previously it had a hard dependency on it
	  so for most people it would simply crash when started.  It also no longer tries to buffer the sound
	  files itself; this fixes the stuttering issue (although it seems DirectSound preloads the entire file
	  now, causing a noticeable delay when starting playback, and also causing a marked increase in memory
	  use).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.2 Released" author="Pebbles" date="December 26th, 2004">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.2, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>Current Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Audio Browser - allows playing &amp; decoding of all PlayOnline-related audio files.</li>
	<li>Macro Manager - allows editing of character macro bars (with auto-translator support).</li>
	<li>TetraMaster image viewer - allows viewing (and extracting) of the image files of Tetra Master.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Known Issues:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Macro editing works, but is in a beta stage - I recommend using it on macro bars that are currently
	  empty, to avoid loss of data. Note that you need to explicitly ask the tool to save changes; so it
	  is perfectly safe to simply browse the macros.
	</li><li>
	  POLUtils loads the icons it needs at runtime (from POL and Windows files); if you run anything other
	  than WinXP, they may not look right. If that is the case, let me know (e.g. by sending screenshots
	  and mentioning what OS version you use).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Things I would like:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  The name mappings for the music and sound effect files is incomplete; if you can put a name to any
	  unnamed tracks, let me know.
	</li><li>
	  The "Insert Special Character" and "Insert Faces" context menu entries for the macro command text
	  are not implemented yet. I welcome suggestions, especially for the Faces category (the special chars
	  I can extract from the shift-jis character set).
	</li><li>
	  Any and all suggestions/requests are welcomed (new utility, new feature in existing utility, ...). But
	  please don't request a model viewer (yet) - that's outside the scope of my technical skills for the
	  moment.
	</li><li>
	  If you have the JP client and have Front Mission Online installed, please contact me, so I can get some
	  information from you.
	</li><li>
	  If you have the EU client, let me know - i need to verify some registry settings. If you can provide an
	  ISO or whatever of the EU POL Viewer disc, even better.
	</li><li>
	  Send in your favourite macros, for future inclusion in the standard macro library.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
  </news>
  <!-- Downloads -->
  <downloads>
    <group name="POLUtils - Stable Beta">
      <file name="POLUtils-0.5.1-Release.exe">
	Fixed loading of Managed DirectSound.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.5.0-Release.exe">
	Reworked data browser, removed codepage dependencies, added config editor.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.4.0-Release.exe">
	Added installer, fixed data browser bug, improved localization support.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.3.5-Release.zip">
	Some data browser enhancements: an item data viewer and a menu to easily find some "interesting" files.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.3.0-Release.zip">
	The second release of the POL Utils; introduces an initial version of the FFXI Data Browser.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.2.0-Release.zip">
	The first real release of the POL Utils.<br/>
      </file>
    </group>
    <group name="POLUtils - Support Files">
      <file name="mdxredist.msi">
	The latest version (9.0c, December 2004) of the Microsoft Managed DirectX redistributable.<br/>
	As of version 0.3, the POLUtils Audio Manager component dynamically accesses Managed DirectSound, so
	it no longer depends on a specific version being installed (in fact it should be able to handle its
	absence just fine).  So if you already have an older version installed, it's not required to install
	this as well (but it also doesn't hurt).
      </file>
      <file name="mdxredist-0.2.msi">
	Microsoft Managed DirectX redistributable (9.0b) - needed by the Audio Manager component of POLUtils 0.2.
      </file>
    </group>
    <group name="foo_pol">
      <file name="foo_pol-1.2.zip">
	Fixes playback of PCM sound effects.  Adds recognition for non-PCM, non-ADPCM files (playback of those is
	NOT supported).<br/>
	For use with version 0.8.3 (and compatible) of foobar2000.
      </file>
      <file name="foo_pol-1.1.zip">
	Adds a "fade out" loop mode.<br/>
	For use with version 0.8.3 (and compatible) of foobar2000.
      </file>
      <file name="foo_pol-1.0.zip">
	Version 1.0 of a plugin for the <a href="http://www.foobar2000.org/">FooBar2000</a> audio player that allows
	playback of .bgw and .spw files.<br/>
	For use with version 0.8.3 (and compatible) of foobar2000.
      </file>
    </group>
    <group name="Other Stuff">
    </group>
  </downloads>
  <!-- Links -->
  <links>
    <group name="Info Sites">
      <link target="http://ffxi.somepage.com/" name="SomePage">Great resource repository, updated frequently.</link>
      <link target="http://mysterytour.web.infoseek.co.jp/ffxi/us/" name="MysteryTour">One of the most comprehensive FFXI sites.</link>
      <link target="http://ffxi-atlas.com/" name="Vana'diel Atlas">The only map site you'll ever need.</link>
    </group>
    <group name="Forum Sites">
      <link target="http://ffxi.killvoid.com/" name="KillingIfrit">
        One of the main FFXI forums; high moron and flame count, occasional nugget of useful info.
      </link>
      <link target="http://www.ffxionline.com/" name="FFXIOnline">
        Like KillingIfrit, but with greatly reduced moron and flame count, and more useful info.
      </link>
    </group>
  </links>
</website>
