<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!-- $Id$ -->
<website name="Pebbles&apos; Program Page" url="http://users.telenet.be/pebbles/" news-feed="news.rdf">
  <!-- News Items -->
  <news file="news.html">
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.7 Released" author="Pebbles" date="July 8th, 2008">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.7, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>Only minor tweaks, no major changes. Consider this the "final" version - I don't expect
         there to be any versions after this (I have some offers regarding continued fixes for
         formats broken by patches, but we'll have to see if/how that pans out).</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.6 Released" author="Pebbles" date="March 11th, 2008">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.6, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>Updates item loading for the DAT changes in the March update.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.5 Released" author="Pebbles" date="December 8th, 2007">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.5, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>This improves WotG support in the data browsers (maps aren't catalogued yet), and
         adds macro book support to the macro editor.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.4 Released" author="Pebbles" date="November 20th, 2007">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.4, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>Not too many changes this time, mainly fixing the loading of the armor DATs, and
         adding some extra field values (DNC, SCH for jobs, SoulPlate and Reflector for item
         types).</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.3 Released" author="Pebbles" date="June 11th, 2007">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.3, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>A new utility was added which allows editing npc/monster names (which violates the TOS,
         so use at your own risk). Also, the data browser was updated with new DAT locations,
         and adds the French &amp; German DATs as well.</p>
      <p>Note that support for the new DATs is fairly rough (the raw string tables are shown),
         and some of the related resource strings (as seen in the macro editor) are not supported
         properly yet. Also, because of the various new DAT formats, EngrishOnry has been
         disabled until I take it upon myself to redo it for full EN-FR-DE-JP resource switching
         including support for the new DAT formats.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.2 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 7th, 2007">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.2, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>The only changes here are fixed item &amp; autotrans translation in EngrishOnry, and
         an update of the German translation.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.1 Released" author="Pebbles" date="December 20th, 2006">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.1, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>There are some changes under the hood, but the main reason for this release is the
         DAT changes of the 20061218 patch.  EngrishOnry currently has its item and autotrans
         translation disabled (both are broken); I may push a 0.9.2 release before the end of the
         year with a working EngrishOnry.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="DAT Format Changes" author="Pebbles" date="December 18th, 2006">
      <p>Today's patch changed the Item and Status DAT formats (as well as the string table format),
         breaking POLUtils - this is being worked on.  In the meantime, do NOT use Engrishonry as
         it will corrupt the item data.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.9.0 Released" author="Pebbles" date="July 25th, 2006">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.9.0, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>This is mainly a bugfix release; there aren't many new features.  Support was added
         for Mob/NPC lists; that's about it.  Some of the ROM mappings were fixed, and clipboard
         access was finally fixed (so stuff you copy will stay there after POLUtils closes).</p>
      <p>POLUtils is now available as two separate builds - one for x86 (32-bit) systems and
         one for x64 systems (no Itanium build, sorry).  Unfortunately only Managed DirectX 2.0
         supports x64, and its interface is completely different from that of MDX 1.0, so the
         x64 build currently does not support audio playback.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.8.3 Released" author="Pebbles" date="April 25th, 2006">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.8.3, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>This version adds (almost) full ToAU support; most dialog tables are known by EngrishOnry
         and the data browser, and most map DATs are listed as well.  In addition, some of the
	 other DAT fields were adjusted (most notably some changes to the Abilities info, and
	 the addition of PuppetItem items).</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.8.2 Released" author="Pebbles" date="March 21st, 2006">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.8.2, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>This version corrects the Strange Apparatus Passcode generator - the one in 0.8.1
         listed the wrong elements (the codes were correct for each given zone though).</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.8.1 Released" author="Pebbles" date="March 20th, 2006">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.8.1, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>New component: a passcode generator for the Strange Apparatuses.</li>
        <li>The AudioManager has been changed to incorporate the buffering playback used by the
            oldest POLUtils version.  If this buffered playback is used (the default), all tracks
            (well, except the ATRAC-3 ones, of course) will be playable (no more exceptions on the longer
            ones) and consume far less memory.  As a drawback, playback will skip if another DirectSound
            application (WinAmp, POL Viewer, ...) is active at the same time, and there is a bug that
            causes the last second or so of some tracks to loop.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>An issue that prevented correct POL detection on some systems has been resolved.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p>Microsoft has a new DirectX SDK available, which includes a version of Managed DirectX
         that targets .NET 2.0.  I'll be testing that out shortly; if all goes well, that means
         audio playback will be available on 64-bit systems starting from the next version of
         POLUtils.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="Forums Created" author="Pebbles" date="March 10th, 2006">
      I've set up a simple forum at <a href="http://polutils.forumer.com/">polutils.forumer.com</a> -
      feel free to head over there &amp; register.
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.8.0 Released" author="Pebbles" date="February 23rd, 2006">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.8.0, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>It's fairly light on new features; the main thing is a complete rewrite of the core DAT
         loading code, to make the various forms of data accessible in a generic way.<br/>
         From the user's point of view, this currently mainly manifests itself as an ability to
         export pretty much any supported DAT type to XML.  0.9.0 will see the item find dialog
         replaced by a generic version, making text searches possible in the dialog tables, for
         example; and the item list comparison tool will also be made generic.<br/>
         As a side-effect, the XML format has been changed once again, but should now be stable;
         as with 0.7.0, the ItemListUpgrade utility will convert old files to the new format.
         CSV Export is currently unavailable.</p>
      <p>The German translation of the main UI, and the German, Spanish and French installer translations
         are included.  The old and extremely incomplete Dutch &amp; Japanese UI translations were removed.
      </p>
      <p>POLUtils will run natively on Win64 and should now correctly detect POL &amp; FFXI on those systems.
         Audio playback will probably be unavailable until Microsoft released a 64-bit version of Managed
         DirectX.  I may switch to using specifically 32-bit targeted builds in future releases to avoid
         further issues on Win64.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="More Translation News" author="Pebbles" date="February 16th, 2006">
      The installer can now speak Spanish and French (thanks to Kapibara from the Phoenix server);
      translations for the tools themselves are in progress, but probably won't make it into 0.8.0
      (which is slated to be released next week after the patch).
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="Status Update" author="Pebbles" date="February 5th, 2006">
      The rewrite of the core file content handling is pretty much completed; as a result, it will
      be much easier for me to handle any changes S/E may make to the file format in future patches.
      In addition, it will be possible to export the data from any file format supported by the data
      browser to XML, making it much easier to detect the changes made by a patch.  In fact, one of the
      main remaining tasks is to rework the item comparison app to handle comparing other data too.
      I would expect that 0.8.0 will be relesed shortly after ther February patch (there's bound to be
      some data changes in that).
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="German Translation In Progress" author="Pebbles" date="January 18th, 2006">
      A volunteer has stepped forward to provide a German translation of POLUtils - the installer has
      been covered already, with the full UI to follow soon.  A round of applause for Andy Müller
      (Missingno on Fairy) please!<br/>
      As always, volunteers for translations are most welcome (French and Spanish already have a candidate,
      but that leaves many languages to choose from).  In fact, I'd especially like people to do a Japanese
      translation - I'll probably remove my partial bits of Japanese and Dutch translation from the next
      release.
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.7.0 Released" author="Pebbles" date="December 24th, 2005">
      <p>This is the next baseline release; it's not much more than a .NET 2.0 build of POLUtils 0.6.4.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Built using .NET 2.0; some UI tweaks have been made to match this switch (nothing major yet).</li>
	<li>Integrated EngrishOnry into POLUtils.</li>
        <li>Added ItemListUpgrade, a simple utility that converts an "old" item list XML dump to the current format.</li>
        <li>CSV Item Export now puts in Description as a single multiline field (tested import with Excel and Access),
	    and will always include the item's icon info.</li>
	<li>If anyone's interested in providing translations for POLUtils, a kit is now available (in the
	    downloads section). Note that translating anything except the installer requires Visual Studio 2005
	    (might work with Visual C# 2005 Express too, but that is untested).<br/>
	    Do let me know before you start working on this (to avoid duplicate efforts).</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="RSS Feed Added" author="Pebbles" date="December 24th, 2005">
      Added an RSS feed for the news items; this allows you to add live bookmarks or to put the news items on
      your Google home page.
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.6.4 Released" author="Pebbles" date="December 15th, 2005">
      <p>Another emergency release - turns out S/E also changed the autotranslator file's structure, breaking
         EngrishOnry's autotrans translation as well as the Macro Editor component of POLUtils.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.6.3 Released" author="Pebbles" date="December 13th, 2005">
      <p>An emergency release due to the data changes for items and spells of yesterday's patch.
         Note that the spell data now has 24 slots for job level, up 8 from the previous layout, so it seems like
         S/E is keeping its options open for possible future expansions (although they've said in the past that
         they probably wouldn't do more than 3 expansions).</p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>EngrishOnry had non-functional ability translation; this is now fixed.</li>
	<li>The item viewer control had some broken behaviour (layout issues), this is now fixed.</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="Refreshed 0.6.2 Installer" author="Pebbles" date="December 5th, 2005">
      I uploaded a fresh installer, which returns to the "old-style" .NET detection, and allows installation to continue if the
      detection fails.  This should resolve the problems people reported.<br/>
      In other news, I may release 0.7.0 soon - this will simply be 0.6.2 but built for version 2.0 of the .NET framework. It may
      end up being one of the last releases, because I am seriously considering quitting the game (I haven't played in over a month);
      let's hope the holidays + december patch can draw me back in.
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.6.2 Released" author="Pebbles" date="November 20th, 2005">
      <p>After a looooooong delay (caused by ZoneAlarm-induced BSOD issues), I'm back with another minor update (0.6.2).</p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>The autotranslator translation of EngrishOnry was fixed (it broke the game, making text input impossible).</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>EngrishOnry was made more configurable. For example, in the case of the autotranslator translation, you can choose to keep the
	    Japanese abbreviations (e.g. "ari&lt;TAB&gt;" to get "(Thank you.)").</li>
        <li>Thanks to some digging by Stephen Newby, several new fields were added to the item viewer (including element &amp; storage size on
            furniture items).  One of the fields applies specifically to beastmaster "jugs"; it's currently marked as "jug size" (with a
            value ranging from 1 to 5 much like shield size), but its exact meaning has not yet been determined.  For all I know it could be
            a pet damage or summon time multiplier.  Any feedback from BSTs is appreciated.</li>
        <li>The text for quests/missions/key items is now viewable (from the String Table menu), bringing POLUtils closer to matching ffxitool's
         non-3D functionality.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><em>Note</em>: the XML output format has changed in this version (and will hopefully be fairly future-proof).  I may release a small
         tool to "upgrade" existing exports, but it's not a priority for me at this time.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.6.1 Released" author="Pebbles" date="August 2nd, 2005">
      <p>Just a quick bugfix release - fixes dialog and string table translation in EngrishOnry,
         and corrects/extends the list of dialog tables in the data browser.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.6.0 Released" author="Pebbles" date="July 31st, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.6.0, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>If you have remarks/comments/gripes/corrections/suggestions/whatever, please, please let me know
         (email is on main page).</p>
      <p>I'm also interested in DAT file mappings - if you know what a particular DAT file contains, and it's
         not yet linked to from the data browser menu, let me know.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Includes EngrishOnry, a small utility that allows you to translate pieces of the Japanese interface,
	  making use of the JP POL client more comfortable for native English speakers.  Because this utility
	  modifies and/or swaps DAT files, it violates the TOS, so use at your own risk.  Note that it is merely
	  installed alongside POLUtils (if selected in the installer) - no shortcuts for it are created.
	</li><li>
	  Includes an Item Comparison tool - this allows comparing XML exports of item data (useful after a patch
	  to find new/changed items).
	</li><li>
	  Several more bits of info are show (such as improved ability &amp; status info, and spell info) - most of these
	  are linked from the "String Tables" menu in the data browser.
	</li><li>
	  The casting time of enchanted items is now listed as well.
	</li><li>
	  List views now autosize themselves.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Known Issues:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Some of the dialog tables linked to from the menu aren't shown (no viewers available). This is being looked into.</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="foo_pol 1.3 Released" author="Pebbles" date="July 31st, 2005">
      <p>This release fixes the borked configuration page.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="foo_pol 1.2 Released" author="Pebbles" date="July 22nd, 2005">
      <p>As of the July patch, S/E has been using ATRAC-3 for music and sound effects in FFXI.
         I updated foo_pol to recognize those files, but it's unable to play them (ATRAC-3 is a
         proprietary codec by Sony; why they use it is beyond me as it's worse than MP3 quality-wise - they
         should have gone for Ogg Vorbis instead).  Unless some major bug is found, this will probably
         be the last foo_pol release until foobar2000 0.9 comes out.</p>
      <p>I also plan to move up the POLUtils 0.6.0.0 release - it won't have all the features I would
         like, but should be nice nonetheless.  It will also include EngrishOnry, a small utility
         to translate portions of a JP FFXI installation.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="Still not dead" author="Pebbles" date="July 6th, 2005">
      <p>POLUtils still isn't dead, I've just been doing other stuff; there's not much to report
         at the moment.  0.6.0.0 will be done when it's done.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.5.1 Release" author="Pebbles" date="May 6th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.5.1, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Fixed broken loading of Managed DirectSound.</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.5.0 Release" author="Pebbles" date="May 1st, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.5.0, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p>If you have remarks/comments/gripes/corrections/suggestions/whatever, please, please let me know
         (email is on main page).</p>
      <p>I'm also interested in DAT file mappings - if you know what a particular DAT file contains, and it's
         not yet linked to from the data browser menu, let me know.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Improved installer; added warning message to make sure people only use installers they
	  dowload from the official page.
	</li><li>
	  Fully implemented character set conversion using internal translation tables - this means POLUtils
	  no longer depends on any Windows codepages; it should be fully Unicode.  There will probably still
	  be gaps in the extended mappings added by SE; if you see any &lt;BAD CHAR: xxxx&gt; markers, please
	  report them (and if possible, let me know what character shouldve been shown instead).
	</li><li>
	  Lots of improvement to the data browser.  The item viewer was completely overhauled, and a
	  "find item" dialog was added, with moderately poweful query capability.  Exporting item data
	  to XML or CSV is also fully supported (no progress window for it yet though).  Several more
	  string table formats are supported (titles, abilities, area dialog tables).
	</li><li>
	  The data browser has 2 settings of its own (not currently preserved between runs) - you can
	  opt to see a more detailed progress report (e.g. "loaded 5/200 items" instead of "loading items..."),
	  and you can choose to make the file scan abortable.  Either option slows down the file scans though,
	  so they're disabled by default.
	</li><li>
	  Added FFXI Config Editor.  Currently allows changing only resolution and sound effect count
	  (free editing, not limited options).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>New Bugs:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Lots. Probably.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Too many to mention.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Plans For Next Release</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Overhaul the macro editor.  If you have any layout/design suggestions, please let me know.
	</li><li>
	  Rework the menu system for the data browser, perhaps basing the menus completely on an XML file
	  that describes known DAT files.
	</li><li>
	  Rework the audio manager so that it doesn't do a full scan, but instead only scans parts of the
	  directory tree on an as-needed basis.  While not much an issue for the music files, scanning the
	  SFX files takes waaaay too long.
	</li><li>
	  (Maybe) Add a recipe database.
	</li><li>
	  Add a tool to compare exported item lists (mainly for my own use, so that i can report item data
	  changes after each patch).
	</li><li>
	  (Maybe) Extend the config editor to allow full configuration (would help people that use JP POL +
	  NA POL + 1 FFXI install, as that means no JP FFXIConfig).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="I ATEN'T DEAD" author="Pebbles" date="March 6th, 2005">
      <p>No, the POLUtils project isn't dead.  I am rewriting a lot of stuff (data browser, macro editor)
         and am writing a text decoder from scratch (good: no more codepage dependencies, bad: lots of
         boring mapping table data entry).  On top of all that, I plan to add an FFXI config editor
         (resolution / sample count already in; also looking into other stuff) and an item search (i.e.
         look for all items containing "Aketon" in their name or "Ranged Accuracy" in their description).</p>
      <p>This is all going to take some time, and I'm not going to release 0.5.0 until that's finished;
         so bear with me ^^.</p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="foo_pol 1.1 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 20th, 2005">
      <p>I'm release an update to foo_pol today. Nothing spectacular, but rather useful.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  There is a new "Fade Out (10 seconds)" loop option.  For looped files, this will cause
	  it to loop for a maximum of 10 seconds, with a slow fade.  This makes listening to looped
	  tracks more pleasant.  This feature was suggested by Feenicks on the FFXIOnline forums.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.4.0 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 16th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.4.0, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  POLUtils is deployed via an installer now - this also checks for the presence of the .NET
	  framework 1.1, to avoid unexpected and/or cryptic Windows errors.
	</li><li>
	  The language choice on the main dialog will now only list available options (and in its
	  native form).  Additionally, the selection will be preserved across runs.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  There was a logic error in the data browser - if a second item data file was opened, the
	  item icons of the first one were reused.  This is now fixed.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.3.5 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 15th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.3.5, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.<br/>
         This is really an intermediate release, there weren't enough major changes to
         warrant a 0.4 version.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  The data browser has a menu now, that allows you to easily find several kinds of "interesting" files
	  (maps, item data, etc.).
	</li><li>
	  The data browser now has support for item data - not quite all available info has been figured out
	  at the moment (e.g. Rare/Ex/NoAuction flags).
	</li><li>
	  The data browser will now scan files for any images they may contain (instead of just checking the
	  start of the file and displaying the first one it found).  Unfortunately, this can take some time,
	  and you cannot abort the scan at the moment.  I will look into making that more convenient (improving
	  the speed probably won't be possible, but I'll try the too) - however, threading doesn't play very
	  nice when Windows Forms controls are involved, so it's a bit tricky.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Some of the picture loading code was broken and/or missing - the current data browser should
	  support most formats (DXT1-DXT5 and the various bitmaps) properly.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.3 Released" author="Pebbles" date="January 4th, 2005">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.3, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>New Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  You can select the interface language - only small portions have been localized at the moment,
	  and only for Dutch and Japanese.  Volunteers will be needed to assist further.
	</li><li>
	  FFXI Data Browser - allows browsing the contents of the .DAT files of FFXI.<br/>
	  Currently, only string tables (e.g. ROM\97\17-57.DAT) and maps (e.g. ROM3\4\0-20.DAT) will be shown
	  (although some non-map images will also be shown (e.g. ROM\0\1.DAT, which contains the game's font,
	  and ROM\97\10.DAT, which has the treasure chest texture).<br/>
	  I'll probably add menus in the next version to help locate "interesting" files.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Fixes:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  POLUtils will refuse to start if no POL clients are installed (instead of crashing).
	</li><li>
	  The AudioManager now dynamically loads Managed DirectSound - previously it had a hard dependency on it
	  so for most people it would simply crash when started.  It also no longer tries to buffer the sound
	  files itself; this fixes the stuttering issue (although it seems DirectSound preloads the entire file
	  now, causing a noticeable delay when starting playback, and also causing a marked increase in memory
	  use).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
    <news-item title="POLUtils 0.2 Released" author="Pebbles" date="December 26th, 2004">
      <p>Today I'm releasing POLUtils 0.2, a collection of PlayOnline-related utilities.</p>
      <p><strong>Current Features:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>Audio Browser - allows playing &amp; decoding of all PlayOnline-related audio files.</li>
	<li>Macro Manager - allows editing of character macro bars (with auto-translator support).</li>
	<li>TetraMaster image viewer - allows viewing (and extracting) of the image files of Tetra Master.</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Known Issues:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  Macro editing works, but is in a beta stage - I recommend using it on macro bars that are currently
	  empty, to avoid loss of data. Note that you need to explicitly ask the tool to save changes; so it
	  is perfectly safe to simply browse the macros.
	</li><li>
	  POLUtils loads the icons it needs at runtime (from POL and Windows files); if you run anything other
	  than WinXP, they may not look right. If that is the case, let me know (e.g. by sending screenshots
	  and mentioning what OS version you use).
	</li>
      </ul></p>
      <p><strong>Things I would like:</strong><br/><ul>
	<li>
	  The name mappings for the music and sound effect files is incomplete; if you can put a name to any
	  unnamed tracks, let me know.
	</li><li>
	  The "Insert Special Character" and "Insert Faces" context menu entries for the macro command text
	  are not implemented yet. I welcome suggestions, especially for the Faces category (the special chars
	  I can extract from the shift-jis character set).
	</li><li>
	  Any and all suggestions/requests are welcomed (new utility, new feature in existing utility, ...). But
	  please don't request a model viewer (yet) - that's outside the scope of my technical skills for the
	  moment.
	</li><li>
	  If you have the JP client and have Front Mission Online installed, please contact me, so I can get some
	  information from you.
	</li><li>
	  If you have the EU client, let me know - i need to verify some registry settings. If you can provide an
	  ISO or whatever of the EU POL Viewer disc, even better.
	</li><li>
	  Send in your favourite macros, for future inclusion in the standard macro library.
	</li>
      </ul></p>
    </news-item>
  </news>
  <!-- Downloads -->
  <downloads>
    <group name="POLUtils - Stable Beta">
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.7-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.7-Release-x64.exe">
	Minor tweaks.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.6-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.6-Release-x64.exe">
	Fixed item loading broken by the 20080310 patch.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.5-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.5-Release-x64.exe">
	More WotG support + handle macro books.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.4-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.4-Release-x64.exe">
	Minor DAT loading fixes.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.3-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.3-Release-x64.exe">
	NPC Renamer; French/German DATs.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.2-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.2-Release-x64.exe">
	Fixed EngrishOnry (items, autotrans).<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.1-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.1-Release-x64.exe">
	Bugfixes and NPC/Mob list support.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.0-Release-x86.exe"/>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.9.0-Release-x64.exe">
	Bugfixes and NPC/Mob list support.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.8.3-Release.exe">
	Updated data browser &amp; EngrishOnry for ToAU.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.8.2-Release.exe">
	Corrected the Strange Apparatus passcode generator.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.8.1-Release.exe">
	Strange Apparatus passcode generator, improved audio playback.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.8.0-Release.exe">
	Major core rewrite, minor tweaks &amp; fixes.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.7.0-Release.exe">
	Built for .NET 2.0.  Integrated EngrishOnry + minor cosmetic changes.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.6.4-Release.exe">
	Updated for the changed autotranslator file structure of the 20051212 patch.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.6.3-Release.exe">
	Another EngrishOnry fix + updated for the data changes of the 20051212 patch.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.6.2-Release.exe">
	Fixed EngrishOnry and made it more configurable; added several new item fields, and added quest/mission/key item viewing.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.6.1-Release.exe">
	Fixed EngrishOnry; adjusted dialog table lists in the data browser.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.6.0-Release.exe">
	Added an item data comparison tool, and bundled EngrishOnry.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.5.1-Release.exe">
	Fixed loading of Managed DirectSound.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.5.0-Release.exe">
	Reworked data browser, removed codepage dependencies, added config editor.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.4.0-Release.exe">
	Added installer, fixed data browser bug, improved localization support.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.3.5-Release.zip">
	Some data browser enhancements: an item data viewer and a menu to easily find some "interesting" files.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.3.0-Release.zip">
	The second release of the POL Utils; introduces an initial version of the FFXI Data Browser.<br/>
      </file>
      <file name="POLUtils-0.2.0-Release.zip">
	The first real release of the POL Utils.<br/>
      </file>
    </group>
    <group name="POLUtils - Translator's Kit">
      <description>
	This kit can be used to provide me with localized resources for POLUtils (i.e. translations for the
	installer and GUI).<br/>
	Note that for optimal efficiency in doing the translation, Visual Studio 2005 or Visual C# 2005 Express
	is required (otherwise you would not be able to size the controls to match the changed text).<br/>
	The installer texts can be localized with a plain text editor, so you can still contribute if you're
	unable or unwilling to use Visual Studio/C#.
      </description>
      <file name="POLUtils-Localization.zip">Current localization kit.</file>
    </group>
    <group name="POLUtils - Support Files">
      <file name="mdxredist.msi">
	The latest version (9.0c, December 2004) of the Microsoft Managed DirectX redistributable.<br/>
	As of version 0.3, the POLUtils Audio Manager component dynamically accesses Managed DirectSound, so
	it no longer depends on a specific version being installed (in fact it should be able to handle its
	absence just fine).  So if you already have an older version installed, it's not required to install
	this as well (but it also doesn't hurt).
      </file>
      <file name="mdxredist-0.2.msi">
	Microsoft Managed DirectX redistributable (9.0b) - needed by the Audio Manager component of POLUtils 0.2.
      </file>
    </group>
    <group name="foo_pol">
      <file name="foo_pol-1.3.zip">
	Fixes the configuration page.<br/>
	For use with version 0.8.3 (and compatible) of foobar2000.
      </file>
      <file name="foo_pol-1.2.zip">
	Fixes playback of PCM sound effects.  Adds recognition for non-PCM, non-ADPCM files (playback of those is
	NOT supported).<br/>
	For use with version 0.8.3 (and compatible) of foobar2000.
      </file>
      <file name="foo_pol-1.1.zip">
	Adds a "fade out" loop mode.<br/>
	For use with version 0.8.3 (and compatible) of foobar2000.
      </file>
      <file name="foo_pol-1.0.zip">
	Version 1.0 of a plugin for the <a href="http://www.foobar2000.org/">FooBar2000</a> audio player that allows
	playback of .bgw and .spw files.<br/>
	For use with version 0.8.3 (and compatible) of foobar2000.
      </file>
    </group>
    <group name="Other Stuff">
    </group>
  </downloads>
  <!-- Links -->
  <links>
    <group name="Info Sites">
      <link target="http://ffxi.somepage.com/" name="SomePage">Great resource repository, updated frequently.</link>
      <link target="http://mysterytour.web.infoseek.co.jp/ffxi/us/" name="MysteryTour">One of the most comprehensive FFXI sites.</link>
      <link target="http://ffxi-atlas.com/" name="Vana'diel Atlas">The only map site you'll ever need.</link>
    </group>
    <group name="Forum Sites">
      <link target="http://polutils.forumer.com/" name="POLUtils">
        The official POLUtils forums.
      </link>
      <link target="http://ffxi.killvoid.com/" name="KillingIfrit">
        One of the main FFXI forums; high moron and flame count, occasional nugget of useful info.
      </link>
      <link target="http://www.ffxionline.com/" name="FFXIOnline">
        Like KillingIfrit, but with greatly reduced moron and flame count, and more useful info.
      </link>
    </group>
  </links>
  <!-- Site Sections -->
  <section name="Home" file="index.html" motigo="ADNQcQc5tT8Op5L39Ogb1cjZggeQ">
    <para>Welcome to Pebbles&apos; Program Page.</para>
    <para>
      Here you can find several tools written by Pebbles of Pandemonium; they will either be related to
      <acronym title="Final Fantasy XI">FFXI</acronym> Online, or to <acronym title="PlayOnline">POL</acronym> in general.
    </para>
    <news-headlines/>
    <para><span class="link-description">Pebbles can be contacted via email (pebbles DOT pandemonium AT telenet DOT be).</span></para>
  </section>
  <section name="News" file="news.html">
    <news/>
  </section>
  <section name="FAQ" file="faq.html">
    <para>
      <h3>1. What is POLUtils anyway?</h3>
      <p>
        POLUtils is a collection of utilities related to PlayOnline, Square/Enix' online gaming framework.<br/>
        It currently contains:<br/>
        <ul>
	  <li>an audio manager (with POL, TetraMaster and FFXI support - would add FMO support if I could get
	      someone to give me the info)</li>
	  <li>data browsers for Tetra Master and FFXI</li>
	  <li>an offline macro editor for FFXI</li>
	  <li>a configuration editor for FFXI</li>
	</ul>
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>2. What are the system requirements?</h3>
      <p>
        Well, POLUtils requires the .NET Framework 1.1 to be installed, and the Audio Manager has an additional
        dependency on Managed DirectX (part of DirectX 9 or higher) if you want audio playback (and that's a
        rather essential element of that particular tool).  Unfortunately, Managed DirectX is not automatically
        installed along with DirectX - you can find a suitable installer for it on the downloads page.<br/>
        As for Windows version, any version of windows that can install those two dependencies should do (which
        basically means Windows 98 or later).  Future versions of POLUtils may use the 2.0 framework, which will
        probably require Win2K or later.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>3. I get an exception saying Invalid Codepage - why is that?</h3>
      <p>
        FFXI uses a text encoding based on shift-jis, and it seems the .NET framework relies on a Windows code
        page to process shift-jis.  However, the shift-jis codepage isn't installed by default.  You can easily
        install it in one of two ways: either you enable support for East-Asian languages (Control Panel\Regional
        and Language Options\Languages), but that requires 230MB of disk space, or you can just make sure
        codepages 1250, 1251 and 932 are checked on the Advanced tab of the same control panel applet.<br/>
        As of version 0.5.0, POLUtils uses a handwritten encoding handler for FFXI, so no additional codepages
        should be needed.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>4. Why isn't POLUtils available in <em>&lt;insert language here&gt;</em>?</h3>
      <p>
	Easy - noone has volunteered to help with the translation yet.  If you want to provide the translation,
	let me know; all help is appreciated.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>5. Is POLUtils going to steal my passwords or destroy my PC?</h3>
      <p>
	I sure hope not ^^.  POLUtils currently never ever connects to the internet, so your passwords
	are safe.  As for destroying your PC, that's unlikely as well (of course, the .Net framework is
	Microsoft technology, so you never know).
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>6. Will you make a WinAmp plugin for .bgw/.spw files?</h3>
      <p>
	No.  I considered doing so, but decided against it since a) there already is such a plugin, and b) the
	WinAmp SDK is, well, crap (I never realized how great the foobar APIs were until I saw the WinAmp SDK).
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>7. The menus in the Macro Editor only show little squares instead of symbols, but I do have East-Asian supprt installed. Help!</h3>
      <p>
	This probably means you're using an older (pre-XP) version of Windows.  POLUtils has no control over the
	font of its menus; that's handled by the system.  Try setting the menu font (via the Appearance tab of
	the Display properties in the Control Panel) to Tahoma, that should work. If running on Vista, also try
	setting POLUtils to run in XP SP2 Compatibility mode.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>8. What is that EngrishOnry thing?</h3>
      <p>
	EngrishOnry is a utility to help out those people playing the JP version of FFXI who would like most
	of the game to be in English.  It will translate many of the game's assets to make that happen.
      </p>
    </para>
    <para>
      <h3>9. There's a game patch coming up!  How will this affect my use of EngrishOnry?</h3>
      <p>
	Good question.  If there is a patch, you must take two steps to avoid your game becoming corrupted:
	1) Restore all translations BEFORE applying the patch, and 2) Delete EngrishOnry's backup folder
	([FFXI Install Dir]\EngrishFFXI-Backup).  If you fail to do the first step the patch may fail, and
	you may be forced to reinstall the game.  If you fail to do the second, EngrishOnry will be unable to
	Restore the original file (it will restore the file from BEFORE the patch) - again, possibly forcing
	you to reinstall.<br/>
	Note: in some cases you may be able to force a full file check + redownload of corrupted files by
	deleting the "patch.ver" in the FFXI installation directory.  But this is by no means guaranteed.
      </p>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section name="Download Area" file="downloads.html" motigo="ADNQdQo0vLkP4XweMb5W1npl0G7w">
    <para>Here you can download Pebbles&apos; programs.</para>
    <downloads/>
  </section>
  <section name="Links" file="links.html">
    <para>This page contains various links you may (or may not) find useful.</para>
    <links/>
  </section>
</website>
